Guide to the James Marshall Osborn Research Files on Edmond Malone
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Marshall Osborn research files on Edmond Malone
1928-1974
1950-1970
OSB MSS 169
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17.56
(25 boxes)
The collection consists of subject files, photocopies, and card indexes compiled by James Marshall Osborn in the course of his research for a planned biography of Edmond Malone. Contents include a chronologically arranged set of photocopies of Malone correspondence and a highly detailed set of notes on the events in Malone's life.
Osborn, James M. (James Marshall), 1906-1976
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of James Marshall Osborn, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James Marshall Osborn (1906-1976)
James Marshall Osborn, literary historian, founder of the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection at Yale University, and Holstein cattle breeder, was born in Cleveland, Ohio in 1906. He graduated from Wesleyan University in 1928, and joined the investment advisory department of Guaranty Trust in New York. The next year, he married Marie-Louise Montgomery, a graduate of Vassar.
In 1932 Osborn left Guaranty Trust to study for a Master's degree in English at Columbia University. Two years later, the Osborns moved to England with their two sons, and James began to work toward a B.Litt degree at Oxford University. While at Oxford, Osborn pursued his interest in eighteenth-century literary history and began to acquire the literary and historical manuscripts that would form the core of the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection.
Osborn was appointed Research Associate in English at Yale University in 1938; he held the position until his death. He was named Adviser on Seventeenth Century Manuscripts to the Yale Library in 1954, and in 1963, when he began the transfer of his collection to Yale, became the first curator of the Osborn Collection.
Osborn's publications include The Autobiography of Thomas Whythorne (1961); an edition of Joseph Spence's Observations, Anecdotes and Characters (1966); and Young Philip Sidney (1972).
In addition to his scholarly activities, Osborn was also a noted dairy cattle breeder and promoter of Holsteins from 1940 to 1960. He received the D.Litt from Oxford University in 1968, and was named Curator Emeritus of the Osborn Collection in 1972. James Marshall Osborn died in New Haven on October 17, 1976.
Edmond Malone (1741-1812)
Edmond Malone, literary scholar and editor of Shakespeare, was born in Ireland, the second son of a member of the Irish House of Commons and Justice of the Court of Common Pleas. He received his B.A. from Trinity College, Dublin, in 1762, and began studying law at London's Inner Temple in 1763. During his studies, in 1764, Malone met the writer Samuel Johnson, who encouraged his interest in a literary career; however, Malone was financially obliged to return to Ireland, where he practiced law in Dublin.
In 1776, his uncle Anthony Malone died and bequeathed Edmond an annuity of 1,000 pounds. Malone almost immediately ended his legal career and moved permanently to London, although he continued to visit his Irish relatives. Malone assisted George Steevens on the second edition of the Johnson-Steevens Shakespeare; the first volume contained Malone's groundbreaking An Attempt to Ascertain the Order in which the Plays Attributed to Shakespeare Were Written (1778). Malone next edited Shakespeare's narrative poems, sonnets, and apocryphal plays.
As Malone became known in the London literary world, he renewed his friendship with Johnson and became close to several in Johnson's circle, particularly Sir Joshua Reynolds. In 1782 he was elected to Johnson's Literary Club, and was its treasurer from 1784 until his death. As a result of his membership, Malone developed close friendships with several members of Johnson's circle, including Charles James Fox, Charles Burney, Joseph Banks, and James Boswell.
Malone's proposed edition of the complete works of Shakespeare was announced by his friend John Nichols in the Gentleman's Magazine in August of 1783. Malone conducted extensive documentary research, consulting many of the early quartos as well as the folio editions in an effort to establish an authoritative text, and interpreted his findings with historical insight. The resulting Plays and Poems of William Shakespeare was published in 1790 to wide acclaim, although Joseph Ritson, among others, were highly critical of Malone's preference for the text of the first folio over that of the second folio.
While editing Shakespeare, Malone was also aiding James Boswell in his efforts to write the biographical works on Johnson that would make him famous. Malone revised the manuscript of Journal of a Tour to the Hebrides with Samuel Johnson, LL.D and saw it through publication in 1785. For the next six years, Malone provided invaluable support and assistance to Boswell as he wrote the Life of Johnson, editing the text as Bowell produced it, encouraging Boswell through depression and illness, and helping Boswell with the final revisions before its 1791 publication. Malone was one of Boswell's executors, and it was Malone who had Boswell's papers and manuscripts organized and returned to Boswell's family at Auchinleck House when Boswell died in London in 1795.
In 1796, Malone's publication of An Inquiry into the Authenticity of Certain Miscellaneous Papers and Legal Instruments demonstrated convincingly that the sensational "discoveries" of supposed Shakespeare manuscripts by William Henry Ireland were purely modern forgeries, ending Ireland's celebrity.
Malone continued his Shakespeare research in his later years, but interrupted it for a variety of other projects, including editions of the works of Sir Joshua Reynolds and John Dryden. He died on May 23, 1812 in London; his mass of research materials and notes on Shakespeare were edited and published by James Boswell the younger (1778-1822), who also wrote Malone's obituary for the Gentleman's Magazine.
Scope and Contents
The James Marshall Osborn Research Files on Edmond Malone consist of subject files, photocopies, and card indexes compiled by James Marshall Osborn in the course of his research for a planned biography of Edmond Malone.
Arrangement
Organized into three series. I. Research Materials, 1928-1974. II. Index Card Files. III. Oversize
Authors, English -- 18th century; Editors -- Great Britain; Literary historians -- Great Britain; Malone, Edmond, 1741-1812; Osborn, James M. (James Marshall), 1906-1976
- Research Materials, 1928-1974, undated; Series I; 3.67; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The material is arranged in the order in which it was received by the library.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of subject files containing notes, photocopies, and printed material collected by Osborn in the course of his research for a planned biography of Edmond Malone. There is an extensive run of photostats and photocopies of Malone's own correspondence, assembled from various sources and chronologically arranged, followed by copies of letters by friends of Malone.
  - Malone data, undated (Box 1)
  - Queries sent about Malone, 1937-1965 (Box 1)
  - George Steevens - letters and documents concerning him, 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - James Boswell the Younger - 1825 sale catalogue, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Photostats of correspondence - Clinton Papers (Fettercairn), undated (Box 1)
  - David Fairer, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Lady Philippa Sunderlin, undated (Box 1)
  - Hyde, 1964 (Box 1)
  - A.N.L. Munby, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Beattie, Dr. William, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Cape Town, University of, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Huntington, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Shakespeare's Birthplace Museum, Stratford, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Boston Public Library, undated (Box 1)
  - Malone - Confirmation, undated (Box 1)
  - Harvard, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Malone and/or Shakespeare references in 19th century sale catalogues, undated (Box 1)
  - Stratford-upon-Avon, Corporation of Malone and Shakespeare, undated (Box 1)
  - William Windham, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Malone Family Baronston Branch" from "The Annals of Westmeath", undated (Box 1)
  - Mrs. Malone snr., undated (Box 1)
  - Catherine Malone, undated (Box 1)
  - Colin Clair notes, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Harriet Malone, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes on Malone's annotations to Dr. Johnson's Dictionary, undated (Box 2)
  - Edmund Burke, undated (Box 2)
  - George Hardinge, undated (Box 2)
  - Books owned by Malone, undated (Box 2)
  - R.G. Sawyer notes and correspondence, 1946 (Box 2)
  - "The Club", 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Articles on Malone, 1940-1964 (Box 2)
  - Verses on "The Club", 1972 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous photostats, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Malone - Outline, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with no mention of Malone, undated (Box 3)
  - Illegible xeroxes, scraps, undated (Box 3)
  - Wills of Henrietta and Catherine Malone, Lady Sunderlin, undated (Box 3)
  - Ancillary materials in Folger manuscripts, undated (Box 3)
  - Illustrations for Malone book, undated (Box 3)
  - Commemorative plaque notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Dr. Samuel Parr, undated (Box 3)
  - George Steevens, undated (Box 3)
  - William Temple to Sir William Forbes, undated (Box 3)
  - Malone; book collection, undated (Box 3)
  - Malone's will, undated (Box 3)
  - Malone-Boswell, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Malone Queries, undated (Box 3)
  - Plaque invoice, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Articles on Malone, 1960-1964 (Box 3)
  - London County Council press release on Malone plaque, undated (Box 3)
  - Notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Bodley manuscript Malone notes, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Club", undated (Box 3)
  - Notes from Thorpe's catalogues by individuals, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Edward Malone pedigree, 1944 (Box 4)
  - Malone Miscellaneous, 1938-1948 (Box 4)
  - Notepad, undated (Box 4)
  - General notes from Thorpe's and Magg's catalogues, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Malone on Chatterton and Ireland, undated (Box 4)
  - Questions to be used in character analysis for biographical purposes, undated (Box 4)
  - Malone, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Malone miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Extracts from prefaces etc., undated (Box 4)
  - Malone's chronology of Shakespeare - J.M.Osborn notes, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Early appendices to Dryden F+P, undated (Box 4)
  - Notes - King Lear and Antony and Cleopatra, undated (Box 4)
  - Steevens' Shakespeare notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Coriolanus notes, undated (Box 4)
  - History of stage notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Steevens and Capell notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Malone's Shakespearian activities to 1795, undated (Box 4)
  - Malone chronology, undated (Box 4)
  - Shakespeare miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Dublin plans, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Published items on early editions of Shakespeare, undated (Box 4)
  - Malone family correspondence with J.M.Osborn notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1933-1968 (Box 4)
  - Photostats of Malone-related correspondence
    - Correspondence, January 1752-March 1812, undated (Box 5)
    - "Shakespeare in the Eighteenth Century" by D. Nichol Smith, 1928 (Box 6)
    - George Steevens to Dr. Michael Lort, undated (Box 6)
    - Alexander Boswell and Sir William Forbes, undated (Box 6)
    - Sir Joseph Banks to George Steevens, undated (Box 6)
    - G.B., undated (Box 6)
    - Portland, undated (Box 6)
    - F. Sayers to R. Amyot, undated (Box 6)
    - Euphemia Boswell and Sir William Forbes, undated (Box 6)
    - James Boswell, Jr. and Sir William Forbes, undated (Box 6)
    - Veronica Boswell and Sir William Forbes, undated (Box 6)
    - Alexander Chalmers, undated (Box 6)
    - Reverend James Davenport, Malone's letters to, undated (Box 6)
    - Charles Dilly to Sir William Forbes, undated (Box 6)
    - Sir William Forbes to Thomas Barnard, undated (Box 6)
    - Sir William Forbes to James Boswell, undated (Box 6)
    - Sir William Forbes to T.D.Boswell, undated (Box 6)
    - Charles H. Hunt to Reverend James Davenport, undated (Box 6)
    - William Jephson, undated (Box 6)
    - Newcastle, undated (Box 6)
- Index Card Files, undated; Series II; 10.42; (16 boxes)
  The series consists of several sets of card indexes, including a chronologically arranged and highly detailed set of notes on events in Malone's life ("Malone Chronology") and three boxes of notes on "Malone and Shakespeare."
  - Malone Chronology, undated
    - Malone Chronology 1741-1785, undated (Box 7)
    - Malone Chronology 1786-1790, undated (Box 8)
    - Malone Chronology 1791-1797, undated (Box 9)
    - Malone Chronology 1798-1804, undated (Box 10)
    - Malone Chronology 1805-1812, undated (Box 11)
  - Malone and Shakespeare, undated
    - Malone and Shakespeare (J. Roche's notes), undated (Box 12)
    - Malone and Shakespeare, undated (Box 13)
    - Malone and Shakespeare I, undated (Box 14)
  - MS Malone, undated
    - MS Malone 1-36, undated (Box 15)
    - MS Malone 37-44, undated (Box 16)
  - Malone as a book collector, undated (Box 17)
  - Malone's Life of Dryden, undated
    - Malone's Life of Dryden Index A-O, undated (Box 18)
    - Malone's Life of Dryden Index P-Z, undated (Box 19)
  - Index to Malone MSS in the Bodleian, undated (Box 20)
  - Malone notes (alphabetical), undated (Box 21)
  - Malone - list of correspondents, undated (Box 22)
- Oversize, undated; Series III; 3.47; (3 boxes)
  - Malone notes on Shakespeare in Folger MSS, undated; 15 (Box 23)
  - Malone portrait, undated (Box 24)
  - Photocopies of Malone texts, undated; 9 (Box 24)
  - Malone notes and photocopies, undated; 4 (Box 25)